Guide to the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Member Groups records, 1991-2008 IBT0015
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
IBT Member Groups Records
1991-2011
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America
IBT0015
3 Linear Feet
This collection contains minutes,correspondences,financial records,conference records, photographs and publications created by the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Member Groups. Currently, this collection amasses material relating to the Teamsters Women's Caucus and the National Black Caucus. The material dates from 1991-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains distributed ephemera, minutes, correspondences, notes, financial records, exhibits, and newsletters. These materials cover dates from 1994 to 2002. They are materials from conferences of the International Brotherhood Teamsters Women's Caucus. The IBT Women's caucus, started in 1991, hosts numerous regional conferences every year to advance their goals of equality in the workplace.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Womens Caucus and National Black Caucus
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by International Brotherhood of Teamsters, 2012 [2012.010,2012.011].
Biographical / Historical
There are four member organizations within the International Brotherhood of Teamsters that support and advocate for their constituents on the basis of gender, race, ethnicity and sexual orientation. These are the Teamsters National Black Caucus, the International Teamster Woman's Caucus/Women's Conference, the National Teamsters Hispanic Caucus and the Teamsters GLBT Caucus. The purpose of these groups is to educate themselves and other Teamsters, to communicate with the IBT leadership and the ensure representation at all levels of the organization.
The Teamsters National Black Caucus was formed in 1975. Discussion of forming such a caucus within the IBT dates back to 1971. The goals of the TNBC are: to organize and educate the unorganized in African-American communities throughout the U.S.; to promote affirmative action in the workplace and in African-American communities; to encourage political action and legislation; and to increase black participation in the IBT at all levels.
In November 1986 the Teamsters' Conference on Women in the Workplace was held in Dallas, Texas. The purpose of the conference was to focus on the special needs of women workers in general and Teamster women in particular. In the fall of 1991 a group of Teamster women from the U.S. and Canada formed the International Teamster Women's Caucus (ITWC). The purpose of the Women's Caucus was two-fold. It provided women members the opportunity to become more involved in the workings of the IBT at all levels and it served as a channel of communication and education between Teamster women and IBT leaders. ITWC held its first and only conference in 1995. In 2002 the Teamster Women's Conference was revived on an annual basis with which the Women's Caucus has been closely associated.
Labor unions; Labor; Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women's rights
- Womens Caucus, 1994 - 2001; Series 1; 1.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains distributed ephemera, minutes, correspondences, notes, financial records, exhibits, and newsletters relating to the Internation Brotherhood of Teamsters Women's Caucus. These materials cover dates from 1994 to 2008. They are materials from conferences of the International Brotherhood Teamsters Women's Caucus. The IBT Women's caucus, started in 1991, hosts numerous regional conferences every year to advance their goals of equality in the workplace.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically
  - Women's (Female symbol used) Caucaus [Sic], 1994 December - 1995 March; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Women's (female symbol used) Conference - Atlanta, GA, 1995 June - December; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women's Conferences, 1995 September - December; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Teamster Women's Conference Joint Councils 17 & 46 Buffalo, New York, 1995 October 28; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women's Conference - Recruitment, 1997 September - 1998 June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women's (Female symbol used) Conference General Information, 1998 Feburary - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women's Conference - Meetings/Minutes, 1998 January - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Teamster Women's Conference June 12-14 1998 Cleveland, Ohio, 1998 February - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women's Conference - Registration, 1998 March - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women's Conference - Letters, 1998 February - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1998 Women's Conference - Mailings, 1998 March - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1998 Women's Conference Workshops [1/2], 1998 March - July; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1998 Women's Conference Workshops [2/2], 1998 March - July; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Women's Conference - Speakers, 1998 April - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1998 Women's Conference June 12-14 Exhibit Tables, 1998 April - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Women's Conference Follow-up 1998, 1998 May - June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Women's Conference - Program Book 1998, 1998 June; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Teamster Women's Conference [1/2], 1998 June 12-14; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Teamster Women's Conference [2/2], 1998 June 12-14; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Teamsters Local Union No. 331 1998 Women's Conference, 1998 September 11; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - IBT Eastern Region Meeting, 2000 January - February; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters Women's Confererence 2000 Las Vegas, Nevada [1/4], 2000 March - June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters Women's Confererence 2000 Las Vegas, Nevada [2/4], 2000 March - June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters Women's Confererence 2000 Las Vegas, Nevada [3/4], 2000 March - June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters Women's Confererence 2000 Las Vegas, Nevada [4/4], 2000 March - June; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Teamsters Women's Conference - Las Vegas, NV, 2000 May 19-21; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Teamsters Women's Conference May 19-21, 2000 - Las Vegas, NV, 2000 May - October; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Teamster Women's Conference 2004 Powerpoint, Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women Application For National Membership, 1974; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Women's Occupational Health Resource Center, 1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Differences in Male and Female Psychological Development, 1982; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Working Women's Institute, 1983; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Let's Put The Work Ethic To Work, 5 September 1983; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - A Working Woman's Guide To Her Job Rights, Janaury 1984; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Gender at Work, 1984; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Publications of the Women's Bureau, 1985; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bargaining For Child Care, 1985; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Teamster Conference - Women In The Workplace, 14-16 November 1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Women's Occupational Health Resource Center, April-July 1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Creating Commitment, 28 April 1986; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Women's News, August 2008; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Raising the Stakes, 10 September 2009; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Conference Material, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Organizing The Unorganized, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Political Action and Communtiy Support, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Power on the Job, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Stronger Contracts, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Contract Campaigns, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: miscellaneous, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Organizing For The Future Women's Conference: Conference Information, 12-14 June 1998; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Teamsters Women's Day San Francisco Proclamation, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Teamster Conference on Women in the Workplace Folder, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Women's Conference DVDs, 2007, 2009; Series 1 (Box Shared Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Women's Conference Programs, 2009, 2012, 2015; Series 1 (Box Shared Box 37, Folder 12)
  - Women's Conference Mementos, 2005; Series 1 (Box Shared Box 37, Folder 13)
- Teamsters National Black Caucus, 1991-2011; Series 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains programs, pamphlets, flyers, photographs, position papers, and registration records from the Teamsters National Black Caucus from the period 1991 to 2011. The Teamsters National Black Caucus (TNBC) is a subgroup of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, formed in 1971 to: organize and educate the unorganized in our communities throughout the United States; to promote affirmative action in the work place and in our community; to encourage political action and legislation; and to increase black participation and uphold the principles of the Teamsters' movement and to foster the opportunity for all Teamsters to serve in leadership capacities, throughout the International Brotherhood of Teamsters and the affiliates.
  - Pamphlets and Flyers, 1991; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Position Paper: "An Opportunity to Serve", 1992; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 21st Annual Conference, 1996; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 23rd Annual Conference, 1998; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Registration Rolls, 1999; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 25th Annual Conference, 2001; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 31st Annual Conference, 2006; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 6th Annual Education Banquet Program, 2008; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 36th TNBC Annual Conference, 10 August - 13 August, 2011; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- LGBT Caucus, Series 3
  - Unity, Pride, Strength, & Equality, Undated; Series 3 (Box Shared Box 35, Folder 3)